Inventory of the Mu'assasat al-dhākirah al-'Irāqīyah [Iraq Memory Foundation] records
Hoover Institution Archives
- Appendix: List of Iraqi Testimonies Interviewees with English subtitles, 2007-2008
  - Muwafaq Makki Jasim Al-Musawi, 2007 May 30; 11.27 minutes
    "Born in Baghdad in 1956. An artist and journalist, his father was a poet and his house was like a literary salon. He was expelled from the Fine Arts Institute in 1979 for refusing to join the Ba'th party and was forced to join the military service which caused him severe psychological effects. A few months later, he escaped but was arrested and put in jail. He was transferred to various detention camps. He was sentenced by the military court to death, later the sentence was reduced to 7 years of imprisonment. He has interesting accounts about the suffering of the detainees in the military prisons. This testimony was given in Baghdad on 30-05-2007."
  - Jabbar Mawwat Kassar, 2007 March 16; 11.01 minutes
    "Born in Daynuniyah, he holds a diploma in agronomy from Baghdad University. During his studies he refused to join the Ba'th party so he was harassed. In 1981, after finishing an exam, he got out and the officers were waiting for him, they investigated with him inside the school then he was transferred to Daynuniyah police station where he was tortured and accused of being a member of Al-Da'wah Party. They wrote him a statement and he was forced to sign it. He suffered and was ruthlessly humiliated since he and the group with him were forced to urinate in the container from which they drank water. After 4 months of arrest he was sent to the Revolution court and sentenced to life imprisonment. This testimony was given in Daynuniyah on 16-03-2007."
  - Abd el-Jalil Fateh Osman Omar, 2006 December 10; 11.59 minutes
    "Born in Karkuk in 1958, an underprivileged man. He was arrested in 1979 and accused of being a member of some Turkmen organization. He was charged of writing slogans opposing the Ba'th party. He was subject to various psychological and physical tortures in the General Intelligence Department of Baghdad. A year after his arrest nothing incriminated him except some books considered antagonist. He was transferred to the Revolution Court and sentenced to 20 years of imprisonment which he served all in the special sentences prison in Abu Ghraib while two of his brothers were executed without being charged. This testimony was given Karkuk on 10-12-2006."
  - Abbas Hamza Abbas Al-Maliki, 2007 April 7; 13.36 minutes
    "Born in Al-Hakamiah, Basra, in 1966. He received an engineering diploma in 1989. During the military service he was assigned the cadre of rations in prison number 1, there, he witnessed the amount of cruelty practiced in that prison. He tells painful stories about the torment of the prisoners and some Kuwaiti families. After his discharge, he was appointed an engineer in the Bakr Port. He was arrested in 1999 for unknown reasons and was accused of having connections with the Kuwaiti intelligence. After 5 months of torture, he was presented to court and sentenced to life in prison. After a few days, he was told there had been a mistake and his sentence was reduced to 5 years. This testimony was given in Basra on 07-04-2007."
  - Zakiah Kazim Ismail, 2007 February 1; 7.64 minutes
    "Born in Sadr city the Revolution city formerly, in 1970 her brother Faysal, 19 years old was arrested in 1980 Faysal was horribly tortured for 15 days then he was released. However, he was arrested again two months later and they didn't know anything about him till 2003, when they knew that he was executed. After the execution of her brother she had to leave school and was subject to various security and social harassments. This testimony was given in Baghdad on 01-02-2007."
  - Abd el-Karim Mawlud Ahmad Khodr, 2007 December 8; 7.47 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "Born in Al-Sulaymaniah in 1966 his brother Hussein Mawlud (aka, Mullah Ali) was a poet and member of the Kurdistan National Union organization. He was arrested in the late 70s. Months after his arrest and torture in Al-Sulaymaniah, Karkuk and Mosol camps he was executed in 1979 in Mosol city prison. His body was never handed to his parents. The story didn't end there; after his execution his father was arrested and tortured many times, his arrest lasted once for a year and he was finally exiled from the town where he lived. This testimony was given in Al-Sulaymaniah on 08-12-2007."
  - Shadha Hamid Lilo al-Obeydi, 2007 March 18; 11.47 minutes
    "Born in Al-Diwaniyah in 1961 from a rich family, she was interested in religious education but she wasn't a member in any political party. She was harassed at school for wearing the veil and refusing to join the Ba'th. She was arrested in 1986 and was psychologically and physically tortured. They arrested her for an entire year and she was oddly charged of being a member of an organization working for Iran and Israel. Then, she was referred to the Revolution Court and sentenced for life. She was transferred to Al-Rashad prison where she spent 5 years then she was released on 21-12-1991 upon a pardon. This testimony was given on 18-03-2007."
  - Aqil Yusef Naser, 2007 July 19-20; 8.57 minutes
    "Born in Basra in 1954, an officer in the Naval College. During his preliminary studies, he refused to join the Ba'th and was arrested in 1980 charged with being a member of Al-Da'wah. He endured horrible torture and witnessed the death of a prisoner because of torture. A year after the arrest, he was submitted to the Revolution Court where he was sentenced to death and 5 days later, this was reduced to life. He spent 11 years in the special sentence department in the Abu Ghraib Prison then was released. This testimony was given in Basra on 19-20-07-2007."
  - Aqil Mahdi Miz'al Al-Dirawi, 2007 April 8; 12.59 minutes
    "Born in Shat al-Arab in 1967 from a poor family, an electrical engineer. He didn't belong to any political organization and was forced to join the Ba'th party. He was arrested in 1997 and was beaten and tortured with electric shocks in the security department of Basra till that affected his body structure. He had a surgery in his lung without anesthesia then was transferred to the Basra security department without being accused of anything in particular. He was presented to the Revolution Court and sentenced to life imprisonment, and then the sentence was reduced to 5 years spent in Abu Ghraib. This testimony was given in Basra on 08-04-2007."
  - Sa'id Abdallah Kridi, 2007 March 27; 10.07 minutes
    "Born in Al-Kahlah, Al-Amara in 1953. In August 1983, he was arrested at home and sent to the Fifth Unit prison charged with belonging to the Iraqi Communist party. He endured painful torture and lost a lot of blood during the investigation. He witnessed the horrible torture of a number of prisoners. A few months later, he was submitted to the Revolution Court and was sentenced to 7 years of imprisonment which he spent in Abu Ghraib. This testimony was given on 27-03-2007."
  - Mua'ayed Muhammad Hassan al-Ghabban, 2007 May 18; 9.37 minutes
    "He was born in 1962 in Baghdad from a wealthy family. His father was a merchant and they led a luxurious life. When he was still in intermediate school he was offered to join the Ba'th Party and he turned them down. He was arrested in the early 80s for being involved with someone accused of joining Al-Da'wah Party (Vocation Party). He was extremely tortured and ended up having an infirmity in one of his legs. One year following his arrest he was moved to the Revolution Court and Awwad Al-Bandar sentenced him to life imprisonment. He was jailed for 9 years in the Special Sentences Penitentiary and was detained in a 16m square cell with 65 prisoners. We continued shooting his testimony thanks to a power generator. This testimony was given in Baghdad on 18-5-2007."
  - Ali Fadil Abbas Al-Zubaydi, 2007 May 26; 10.20 minutes
    "He was born in Eastern Karadah in 1956, from a pious family. He was arrested several times from 1975 to 1982, tortured and was never accused of a specific charge. He was arrested for the fourth time in 1982 and was charged with joining Al-Da'wah Party. He was severely beaten up and electrocuted then he was detained in solitary confinement for 8 months. He tried to commit suicide in prison and was tortured when he survived. He was transferred to several prisons then was taken to court and sentenced to life. He spent 10 years of that sentence in Abu Ghraib Prison and was released in 1992. Due to the weak power, we could not have a clear image while shooting. This testimony was given in Baghdad in 26-5-2007."
  - Imad Addin Sadiq Mustafa Husayn, 2006 December 11; 12.13 minutes
    "He was born in Karkuk, in 1960. He was not accepted into the Fine Arts Institute because he was not a member of the Ba'th Party. In 1979, he was convened to the Karkuk police station where he got arrested and was severely tortured all the while unaware of his charge. He was transferred to the General Intelligence Department in Baghdad where he spent 9 months of physical and psychological torture then he was transferred to the Revolution Court and was sentenced by Judge Mulsim al-Jabburi to 7 years in jail. He spent them in Abu Ghraib Prison until this minute he does not know why he was arrested and imprisoned. This testimony was given in Karkuk on 11-12-2006."
  - Amir Ali Yasin, 2007 April 12; 9.36 minutes
    "He was born in Naamaniyyah in 1967 in a big family made of 12 members. In 1979, his two brothers Husayn and Jaafar and his sister Zeinab were arrested then were all executed. Months later, his father was arrested and was quickly executed and the family house was confiscated and the remaining 4 family members were thrown out on the streets. A stranger took them in for 4 years. In 1988, Amir and his mother and 2 sisters Huda and Ibtisam were arrested one of his sisters suffered from a mental disorder in jail. A year later, they were thrown on the Iranian borders and asked to go to Iran on foot and never to return under the false charge of being affiliated to Iran. This testimony was given in the Kut. House on 12-4-2007."
  - Shaza Sabri Nasir, 2007 May 30; 10.18 minutes
    "She was born in Baghdad in 1963. Her father was arrested in 1978 for being a member of the communist party. Two years later, Shaza and her mother were arrested along with her sisters Huda, Nadima, Suha, Nawal and her brothers Ali and the kid Hazim who was 6 years old in addition to her fiancé Mustafa. The security officers occupied their house for 40 days; they stole money and jewelry. According to her the family was tortured psychologically and morally humiliated; all its members were interrogated about the reasons behind their travel to Syria. The family moved from camp to camp for a few months. It later turned out that her father and fiancé were executed. Years later her brother Ali was arrested and is still missing even to the date of this testimony. This testimony was given in Baghdad on 30-5-2007."
  - Jamal Hindar Jadir al-Idani, 2007 April 5; 11.07 minutes
    "He was born in Basra in 1950 he lived the tragedy at an early age. He was 3 years old when his father was arrested in the prison of Nagrat al-Silman. In 1972, his father who was an employer at the harbor facility was arrested again, after 2 years of torture, he was released. Jamal has a brother called Idan he was a Ba'th partisan, he hurt the family immensely; he used to stand against his father after his arrest in 1979. His father was arrested again they did not know anything about him until the fall of the regime when it turned out that he was executed in 1983, his charge remained undetermined. During the filming, nearby gunshots were heard from an unknown source. This testimony was given in Basra city on 5-4-2007."
  - Hamah Hamah Hamah, 2006 December 9; 9.37 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "He was born in the city of Sulaymaniyyah in 1950 from a poor family. He and his family became homeless when his village was air raided. In that raid, his brother and his two nephews were killed. He witnessed continuous bombings and he describes how people resorted to caves and grottos to avoid the bomb showers. He suffered from the arrests that used to take place after bombing the villages with chemical weapons. His brother-in-law was one of the victims and his sister tells us about the bombing and her hard attempts to survive and run away that affected her child who was born handicapped. This testimony was given in Sulaymaniyyah on 9-12-2006."
  - Abdul Sadat Khalaf Al-Basri, 2007 January 12; 8.23 minutes
    "He was born in Maamal in the province of Basra in 1962. He worked as a government employer. He's a writer and member of the association of writers in Iraq. He was a member of a group that formed a cultural forum in Basra whose entire members were arrested, including Abdul Sada. He moved with his fellow writers between several prisons where he was tortured and extremely humiliated with his other colleagues. After about a year of torture and arrest, he was released. He was constantly pursued and placed under surveillance. The power was cut while shooting then we resumed recording this testimony. This testimony was given in Basra in 12-1-2007."
  - Rida Abbas Amin Amin, 2006 December 11; 10.21 minutes
    "He was born in 1962 in the city of Karkuk. In 1981, the security officers and regime's party cadre initiated back then a wide campaign against the Bashir village in which Rida and his family were living. They arrested a number of its citizens including Rida; he was severely tortured in the Karkuk police station and was charged with belonging to the Da'wah Party. He witnessed the death of some detainees while being tortured. After 7 months of arrest he was transferred to the Revolution Court and sentenced to 15 years of jail of which he spent 10 years in the Special Sentences Prison in Abu Ghraib under very harsh conditions where he was periodically tortured. The witness is a Turkman and would rather speak in Arabic for he thought he'd better express himself in Arabic. This testimony was given in Karkuk city in 11-12-2006."
  - Hamid Barir Muhammad Jawad, 2007 April 29; 8.62 minutes
    "He was born in Hollah in 1951. He was subject to several harassments and arrests due to his affiliation with the Iraqi communist party. He was arrested in 1971 on his way to taking his school exam which made him fail that year. He was severely tortured then transferred to Nihaya Castle and there he suffered all kinds of torture for a whole year. He witnessed the shooting of a detainee in Nihaya Castle. Upon his release he was forbidden from finishing his studies because he wasn't a member of the Ba'th party. This testimony was given in Hollah city on 29-4-2007."
  - Muhammad Yasseen Sabti, 2007 April 27; 12.06 minutes
    "Born in the Sunnia part of the Hella district in 1964 to an average family. In 1991, he had a dispute with his brother-in-law who was employed at the presidential palace, the later plotted against him and filed a complaint to the Security Department that led to the arrest of his 3 brothers Rafeh Ismail and Ibrahim and to his own arrest a few days later. No specific charges were pressed; one of the accusations was that they took part in the upheaval. Mohammad was tortured in various ways and then released after one month while his three brothers were executed but that fact was discovered only after the downfall of the regime. This testimony was given on 27/4/2007."
  - Suhayla Kazem Abbas Al-Fatalawi, 2007 May 1; 10.95 minutes
    "Born in Karbala in 1955. During the period when there was a mutual front between Al Ba'th party and the communist party, she was a member of the communist party. In 1977 the Ba'th party started widespread arrests against members of the communist party. Security men tried arresting her so she fled and moved from one place to another. She had to hide along with her husband and child in a room less than 4 square meters. She stayed there from 1979 until 1987. When a political pardon was issued she turned herself in to authorities. The crew that went to record this testimony was caught in a gunfight that lasted for 30 minutes in the Latifiya region and was rescued by the American forces. This testimony was recorded in the city of Karbala on 1/5/2007."
  - Mohammed Youssef Mohammad Jassem, 2007 March 13; 11.09 minutes
    "Born in Al-Dewannyah in 1962, he was arrested and beaten at the age of 17 because two of his relatives were accused of being members of some religious party. He was arrested several times during the 80s and his finger was broken during the torture without ever having any charges pressed against him. In February 2003 he was arrested one more time and accused of being a member of the Sadre movement. He remained in custody for months during which he was tortured in many ways that led to some disfigurations including a broken nose. He was released after the Allied forces went into Iraq. This testimony was recorded in Al-Dewanyah city on 13/3/2007."
  - Ahmad Hassan Anad Al-Ghazzi, 2007 January 16; 9.33 minutes
    "Born in 1951, in the district of Basra. In 1975, his brother Ali was arrested; he was an athlete. He was accused of belonging to the Da'wah Party. Five years after his imprisonment and extreme torture he was released. Ahmad was able to see his brother during his imprisonment and saw the marks that the torture had left on his brother's body ranging from burns to electric shocks. He was arrested once more in 1981 and executed; his body was never handed to his family. Ahmad suffered a great deal after his brother's execution because he had to support his family which comprised 8 persons. This testimony was recorded in Al-Basra city on 16/1/2007."
  - Aswad Hajji Ha De Bamez, 2006 December 15; 9.42 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "Born in Arbil in 1964. He witnessed the events that took place in the Barazan regions in 1974 when the authorities surrounded the Moufty area and then deported all the people there to Al-Dewanya district. Over there, they lived a life of destitution and misery for almost five years. Later they were returned to camps in their areas, the raids started in 1983, his village was attacked by the army and all who were there were arrested including women and children. Aswad was able to escape along with a friend of his, all those who were arrested then were never heard from again. This testimony was recorded in the city of Arbil on 15/12/2006."
  - Abdul Karim Naim Abdul Karim, 2007 January 19; 2007 April 6; 9.23 minutes
    "Born in Abi Al-Khassib kaza in 1959. He was sympathetic with the Da'wah Party but was never a member. He was arrested in 1987 and moved around from one camp to another, he was charged with being a member of Al-Da'wah Party and was brutally tortured. After seven months in detention he was cleared from the charges. In 1994 he was arrested with his father and mother and cousin and was badly tortured for 15 months then he was transferred to the Revolution Court and was sentenced to life in prison. He was taken to the special sentence section in Abu Ghraib Prison where he spent 8 years and was then released after a pardon was issued. Due to security reasons this testimony's recording was halted and then resumed later. This testimony was recorded in the city of Al Basra on 19/1/2007 and 6/4/2007."
  - Safa' Mussallam Bandar Al-Salman, 2007 January 18; 9.00 minutes
    "Born in 1960 in Al-Basrashes, has a Medical Doctor degree her brother Dya' who was a physician was arrested in 1980. In 1981, her brother Ryad refused to join the Ba'th party and was arrested a month later from his classroom at technical school. Her other brother Akil, who was a student at Baghdad's College of Technology was arrested in 1981 and wasn't heard from until the downfall of the regime. Assad, her fourth brother was arrested when he was still a student in an architecture school she did not receive any news of her brothers' whereabouts until the year 2003 when she found out that they were all executed in 1982. They were charged with belonging to the Da'wah Party. She has two more brothers who were imprisoned for 9 years and later released. This testimony was recorded in the city of Al-Basra on 18/1/2007."
  - Nebrass Razzak Hassan, 2007 April 22; 11.31 minutes
    "Born in Al-Dewanya in 1970 his father joined the Ba'th party in 1963 then left the party when he disagreed with its politics so he was pursued and fled to Syria. Nebrass was also a member of the party but was discharged when he missed out on party meetings and then the harassments began. He did not take part in the upheaval in 1991 but he distributed food to some people. After the upheaval there were widespread arrests among young people so he tried to travel outside Iraq but he was arrested. He spent 2 years in detention where he was brutally tortured and lost a lot of weight and contracted many skin and health diseases. This testimony was given in the city of Al-Dewanya on 22/4/2007."
  - Khalaf Abdul-Samad Al Awad, 2007 January 13; 15.35 minutes
    "Born in the city of al-Basra in 1952, he was a university professor who refused to join the Ba'th party so he was hassled. He was arrested in 1977 at the Basra security department then was transferred to the Fadeleya camp where he spent 18 months charged with having sympathies for the Da'wah Party. After his release he left to Algeria and returned in 1982 and went into the military service during that year. He was arrested once again and moved between several camps and finally went to the Head Security Department. He was severely tortured and after one year, he was transferred to the Revolution Court where he was sentenced to life imprisonment of which he served eight. He was released following the issuing of a pardon. This testimony was given in the city of Al-Basra on 13/1/2007."
  - Akil Hadi Kawthar Al-Ghourabi, 2007 March 15; 12.01 minutes
    "Born in the city of Al-Dewaneya in 1972, he has a Bachelors degree in Literature. During his years of study he was placed under surveillance because he did not belong to the Ba'th party and in April 2001 he tried to flee arrest and was shot and fell from the roof. He was transferred to the hospital and underwent many surgeries. 70 days later, he was transferred to the Security Department and was locked in a 2x2m cell. Despite his health condition he was tortured electrocuted and beaten without ever being charged. A year and a half after the arrest he was sentenced to 9 months of imprisonment for possession of religious books. This testimony was recorded in the city of Al-Dewaneya on 15/3/2007."
  - Fatma Majid Hussein Kazem, 2006 December 11; 9.22 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "Born in 1931 in Bechir in the district of Taza, in Karkuk. During the campaign launched on the village of Beshir her five sons were arrested: Aouni Hussein, Ishmael, Khalaf and Sabath, after nine months she was asked to retrieve their bodies one after the other following the execution of four of them. She and her family became homeless and wandered about in many regions after they were thrown out of their home and forced to leave their regions for more than ten years. This testimony was given in Karkuk on the 11th of December 2006."
  - Mehdi Kassem Lafteh Temimy, 2007 April 11; 11.14 minutes